<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copy of a letter, vvritten by M. Doctor Carier beyond seas, to some particular friends in England. VVhereunto are added certaine collections found in his closet, made by him (as is thought) of the miserable ends of such as haue impugned the Catholike Church. To which also is annexed a briefe exhortation to perseuere constantly in the said Catholike Church, what opposition soeuer may occurre, and the danger of liuing out of the same; and lastly, a few examples of the admirable prosperity, of such as haue defended the Catholike Church</title>
            <author>Carier, Benjamin, 1566-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853835</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1060:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copy of a letter, vvritten by M. Doctor Carier beyond seas, to some particular friends in England. VVhereunto are added certaine collections found in his closet, made by him (as is thought) of the miserable ends of such as haue impugned the Catholike Church. To which also is annexed a briefe exhortation to perseuere constantly in the said Catholike Church, what opposition soeuer may occurre, and the danger of liuing out of the same; and lastly, a few examples of the admirable prosperity, of such as haue defended the Catholike Church</title>
                  <author>Carier, Benjamin, 1566-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English Secret Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>"The miserable ends of such as haue impugned the Catholike Church" has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177554:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> Copy of a Letter, vvritten by M. Doctor CARIER beyond Seas, to ſome particular friends in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereunto are added certaine col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections found in his Cloſet, made by <hi>him (as is thought) of the miſerable</hi> ends of ſuch as haue impugned the Catholike <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which <hi>Alſo is annexed a briefe exhortation to</hi> perſeuere conſtantly in the ſaid Catholike <hi>Church, what oppoſition ſoeuer may occurre,</hi> and the danger of liuing out of the ſame. <hi>And laſtly, a few examples of the</hi> admirable proſperity, of ſuch <hi>as haue defended the</hi> Catholike Church.</p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>1615.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177554:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177554:2"/>
                  <head>Pax hominibus bonae voluntatis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y moſt deere and louing friends, if the times were ſuch (as when it ſhall pleaſe God they may be) I would much rather chooſe to haue a poore Vicarage, where I might preach the truth amongſt you, then a rich preferment in any part of the world beſides, where I might not enioy your company and friendſhip. But ſeeing it is otherwiſe, I will lay the fault vpon no body; but rather haue compaſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all, for ſuch is the violence of the ſtreame, that no one man, no not the Maſter of the ſhip himſelfe, is able to ſtirre the ſhip out of the ſtreame: and yet the courſe that is held, is certainely very dangerous; not onely for all the paſſengers that are therin, but euen for the whole veſſel wherin they are carried. If the loſſe of me might haue helped it, I had beene happily beſtowed at home: but ſeeing that my preſence did nothing but procure great danger to my ſelfe euery way, and great anger to them, whoſe game I ſeemed to marre as a ſtander by: I thought it the ſureſt way to ſaue my ſelfe, and to becken to as many of my friends as may pleaſe to beleeue me; that they would alſo looke well about them, loſt they be ouertaken with death, as with a ſtorme, that in ſuch ſommer times doth often come, when it is leaſt looked for; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt all aduentures to conuey themſelues into a ſurer ſhip. I do not deſire they ſhould follow me, and leaue their lands and liuings, their friends and Countrie, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their deare and dread Soueraigne: (and yet if there be no remedie, for the honor of Chriſt and his truth, all muſt be forſaken:) much leſſe doe I allow, that any man ſhould withdraw his allegiance and true ſeruice from King IAMES, and to beſtow it vpon any other Prince, or Prelate in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177554:3"/> world. Only for the dutie I owe vnto God, who hath called me to the knowledge of his truth, and the loue I beare vnto my Countrie, and to all my friends that are therein, I doe moſt humbly and hartily deſire them, that they would ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider and looke to the ſtate of their ſoules, which being immortall, cannot be ſaued by any ſuch religion, as is temporall, mutable, and diſſonant in it ſelfe: And ſeeing no man can be ſaued that dieth out of charitie with his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour (for that an vncharitable ſoule cannot be altered, and made charitable after it is departed.) Let euery good ſoule take heed, how by the railing ſlanders of ignorant, malicious and proud men, it be brought and held out of charitie with a whole Church, and eſpecially ſuch a Church as cannot bee deemed to be the mother of that Church, that is in England; and being a mother Church, it is worthy at leaſt to be heard quietly to tell out her tale at length, before ſhe be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the outcries of thoſe that either of malice, or of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, doe raile vpon her: which I write not that I would haue the Church of Rome gaine by the goods of England, for I know ſhe intends it not, and the State may prouide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; but that I deſire the ſoules of England ſhould gaine by the Church of Rome, which if you might freely heare her ſpeake, you would certainely deſire alſo. And although ſhe may not be ſuffered to ſpeake to you, yet you may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of her: and heare what indifferent men without choler or paſſion doe ſay and write of her. And if you doe find her indeed to be the true Mother, ſuffer not the Diuell to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe your vnderſtanding by hereſie, nor your wills by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, for any worldly reſpect whatſoeuer; but vnite your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of the Church by faith, and your affections to the wil of the Church, by loue &amp; charitie: and if it be poſſible, vnite your outward man alſo to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church, by the participation of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and by al ſpiritual obedience. But if you finde impoſſibilitie therein, then hauing done your beſt to helpe the Catholike Church by your faith &amp; charitie; as S. AVGVSTINE exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177554:3"/> in his booke <hi>de vera relig. cap.</hi> 6. Call vpon Chriſt, who is the immortall Prieſt and Biſhop of your ſoules, that hee would vouchſafe by his abſolute power to ſupply the want of his owne ordinance, and to doe that by himſelfe without Sacraments, which you vnfainedly would, but cannot haue done by any Prieſt of his ſending, and by the Sacraments that he hath appointed: And there is hope that he will doe it, as Saint BERNARD writeth in his booke <hi>de Anima.</hi> This was the Courſe I tooke, vntill God gaue me oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to take a better; for which I humbly thanke his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Maieſtie, and am deſirous to giue all good men ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that haue any religion at all. But I doe conſider that there are, as you may eaſily ſee amongſt your ſelues, foure ſorts of Chriſtians in the world out of the Catholike Church.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Some doe not beleeue either hell or heauen, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are content to goe to any Church, and be of any religion; but care for none at all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Some do beleeue that there is hell and heauen; but that all things fall out by abſolute predeſtination, as by fatall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny, and therefore there is no Church, nor religion can doe a man good, but only to reade Scriptures and heare Sermons and to beleeue that a man is predeſtinate.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Some doe beleeue there is hell and heauen, and that Some religion is neceſſarie; but it is no great matter what; ſo a man obey the Kings Lawes, and liue like an honeſt man. For, they ſay, euery man may be ſaued in his owne religion. All theſe I am out of hope to ſatisfie, although their follies be againſt the light of naturall reaſon, but they haue loſt reaſon.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Some there are that beleeue there is hell and heauen, and that there is no way to auoide the one, or attaine the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but only true Chriſtian Religion, which they would gladly embrace, if they could know which it were. To them, and for their ſakes, I would take any paines to giue ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. And I am certaine, if they will heare mee with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they will be ſatisfied.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177554:4"/>
                  <p>And for the ground of this queſtion; I thinke it will bee granted on all ſides, that, that only is the true Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which our Sauiour Chriſt did teach himſelfe when he was vpon the earth, and which, as he promiſed, ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vntill he come againe.</p>
                  <p>Then the maine care is, to find what religion our Sauiour taught whileſt he was vpon the earth. And heere I would pray euery man of reaſon to conſider:</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That our Sauiour did leaue nothing in writing, but taught his Religion to his Apoſtles by word of mouth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That he commanded not his Apoſtles to write his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but to teach it, <hi>ite praedicate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 That of twelue Apoſtles, ſeuen did leaue nothing at all in writing, but taught their ſucceſſors the Religion of Chriſt by word of mouth.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 That Saint MARKE, Saint LVKE, and Saint PAVL, who wrote moſt of the new Teſtament, were not of Chriſt his company whileſt he was vpon the earth, and therefore muſt needs learne their Religion of the Church, before they wrote it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 That diuers others did write the Religion of Chriſt, as they did apprehend it, but their Goſpels and Epiſtles were reiected by the Church, LVKE 1. 1.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 That at the day of Iudgement, there will be no writing to trie true Religion from Hereſie, but only the eternall truth of Chriſt in the ſoules of his Saints.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 That the Scriptures were written by men of the Church; admitted Canonicall by Councels of the Church; preſerued from Tyrants by the care of the Church, and euer, vntill of late, expounded by the conſent of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 How few men are able to reade and expound the Scriptures any way, and whether it be not eaſier to beleeue the Church, then to beleeue a few priuate men, that ſay they can expound Scriptures better then the Church.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. That all ſorts of Heretikes haue alwaies boaſted of Scriptures, and deſpiſed the Church.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177554:4"/>
                  <p>The Heretikes haue euer beene wont to pretend Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the more eaſily to deceiue the ſimple. They know full well, that all the Fathers, all Doctors, all ancient Writers, all generall Councels, Canons, Traditions, all Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, all Chronicles and monuments of Antiquitie, all Martyrs, Confeſſors, Virgins, and all teſtimonies both in heauen and earth are flat againſt them; and therefore they will pretend the word of God, which they know is a plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſwaſion to the ſimple; and ſo they delude, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them more eaſily. Theſe Scriptures they miſinterpret, corrupt, falſiſie, and abuſe moſt ſhamefully to ſerue their turnes, as VINCENTIVS LI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>INENSIS moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſheweth in his golden treatiſe, <hi>Contra prophanas haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum nouitates,</hi> againſt the prophane nouelties of hereſies.</p>
                  <p>Vpon theſe conſiderations any man may aſſuredly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, that whoſoeuer beleeueth not the Church of Chriſt, can neuer come to know what is the Religion that Chriſt did teach; and which he hath hitherto maintained.</p>
                  <p>And therefore it is impoſſible for ſuch a man to know which is the true Chriſtian Religion. The meanes then to know which is the true Religion of Chriſt, is to enquire which is the true Church of Chriſt. Heere it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that that is the true Church of Chriſt, which Chriſt himſelfe did found whileſt he was vpon the earth, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vntill the worlds end. And whatſoeuer Church is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any other authoritie, then that which Chriſt left vnto his Apoſtles only, cannot be the true Church of Chriſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all the Princes in the world would agree to make it ſo, and cauſe all their ſubiects to ſweare it were ſo.</p>
                  <p>Now to know which is the true Church our Sauiour did found, we muſt obſerue that this word Church doth ſignifie diuers things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Sometimes the Church doth ſignifie the building or houſe of Gods ſeruice; in this ſenſe our Sauiour founded no Church by himſelfe, but gaue power to his Apoſtles and Diſciples to found and conſecrate Churches, as countries ſhould be conuerted.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:177554:5"/>2 Sometime the Church doth ſignifie the Congregation of all thoſe that are baptized, as the Church of Corinth, Rome, &amp;c. in Saint PAVLS Epiſtles. In this ſenſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour founded no Church by himſelfe, for he baptized none, but gaue power to his Apoſtles and Diſciples to baptize.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Sometime the Church doth ſignifie the Clergie or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualtie, choſen out of the number of all Chriſtians, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence the grace of Chriſt committed to them, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the whole bodie: In this ſenſe our Sauiour did by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe immediatly found a Church, when he did call and ſend his Apoſtles, and did giue them the ſame power which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as Man, had receiued of his Father, <hi>Sicut pater miſit me, ſic ego mitto vos,</hi> Ioh. 20. <hi>qui audit vos, me audit,</hi> Luke 10. <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum peccata remiſeritis, remittentur eis,</hi> Ioh. 20. <hi>mittam vobis Paraclitum quivos ducet in omnem veritatem,</hi> Ioh. 14. <hi>Super hanc Petram aediſicabo Eccleſiam,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Then to know which is the true Church, we muſt enq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> which is the Clergie that was founded by Chriſt, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth in the vnitie of the Church by perpetuall Succeſſion from the Apoſtles, &amp; ſo from Chriſt himſelfe: &amp; for your cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine reſolution hereof, you haue three infallible arguments.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The report of Chronicles and Hiſtories, whereof there is great variety, that can tell you the beginning and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euery Schiſme, if you doe but turne the bookes ouer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The vniuerſalitie, antiquitie and conſent of Doctrine taught in the true Church, and the variety, nouelty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie of Doctrine taught in Schiſme, &amp; herein you may inquire of the moſt learned, and moſt honeſt to informe you.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>3 The Scriptures</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <label>1</label>
                           <item>Of the old Teſtament, to which our Sauiour ſends vs, IOH. 5. <hi>Scrutamini Scripturas.</hi> By thoſe S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> proues the viſibility of the Catholike Church againſt Donatiſts.</item>
                           <label>2</label>
                           <item>Of the new Teſtament: by which is proued the perpetuity of the Catholike Church. <hi>Portae inferi non praeualebunt.</hi> Matth. 16. <hi>Vſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> ad conſummationem ſeculi.</hi> Matth. 28.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177554:5"/>
                  <p>Conſider then, deare friends, what a happy thing it is for a man to liue in ſuch a Church, that is, with ſuch a Clergie, as being lawfully called, and continuing in the vnity of the Church, haue the very ſame power that the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; yea that Chriſt himſelfe, as he was Man, had to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes vnto the penitent; to conuey grace by Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as Chriſt conueyed it himſelfe ſometime without Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, to exhibite the Reall preſence of Chriſt vnto the faithfull, and to preach the glad tidings of ſaluation both by word and writing. And on the contrary ſide, what an vnſpeakable miſery it is to haue ſuch a Clergie, that is, ſuch a Church as hath no calling but from a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Magiſtrate, and conſequently no power from Chriſt, no remiſſion of ſinnes, no grace in Sacraments, no Reall preſence of Chriſt amongſt them, nor warrant from Chriſt either to preach or expound the Scriptures; although they talke of them neuer ſo much. I will not determine againſt the ſucceſſion of the Clergie in England, becauſe it is to me very doubtfull; but although the ſucceſſions were neuer ſo good, if there be not vnitie, there can be no grace conueyed from the head vnto ſuch parts of the body as are by Schiſme cut off, and with hoſtilitie oppoſed; as you ſee moſt of the Clergie of England to be. Whileſt my ſelfe was amongſt you, I did what I could to reduce vnity, and to withſtand Schiſme, and therefore I hope God hath conueyed ſome grace by my Miniſtrie amongſt you; but if you conſider du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the premiſſes, you cannot condemne me for taking a ſurer courſe for my ſelfe, eſpecially ſeeing you cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant how much I was maligned, and oppoſed by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and maintainers of Schiſme. It is a continuall griefe to me, that I cannot preach vnto you: And I pray God ſo moue the hearts of his Maieſtie and the Parliament, that it may not be treaſon, nor felonie to be a Catholike Prieſt, nor to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſucceſſion of Saint PETER. nor to preach Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it is held in the Church of Rome, according to all antiquitie, with one vniuerſall conſent. And if euer I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177554:6"/> may be ſo happie to heare ſuch newes, I will thinke my ſelfe moſt happie that I may ſerue you, and liue and die amongſt you. Otherwiſe I will continue as I doe, euery day to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you at the oblation of Chriſts body and bloud, and with my moſt ardent deuotion to pray for his Maieſtie, the Queene, their Children, and Lords of the Councell, my friends at the Court, my louing, and beloued neighbours in the Countrie, and your ſelfe eſpecially; and euer ſo I remaine.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt affectionate and true friend and ſeruant in Chriſt Ieſus. B. A. CARIER.</signed>
                     <dateline>Leidge, <date>February 20. 1614. Stilo Nouo.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177554:6"/>
                  <p>The miſerable ends of ſuch as haue impugned the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church: Together <hi>With the admirable proſperity</hi> of ſuch as defended the ſame.</p>
                  <bibl>Deuter. 32.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laudate Gentes populum eius quia ſanguinem ſeruorum ſuorum vlciſcetur, &amp; vindictam retribuet in hoſtes eorum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You Gentiles praiſe his People, becauſe he will reuenge the bloud of his Seruants, and will repay vengeance vpon their Enemies.</p>
                  </q>
                  <bibl>Eſay 60. 12.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>Gens, &amp; Regnum quod non ſeruierit tibi, peribit.</p>
                     <p>The People and Kingdome, which will not ſerue thee, ſhall periſh.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>1615.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177554:7"/>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:177554:7"/>
                  <head>The miſerable ends of ſome notorious Enemies, of <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his <hi>CHVRCH.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REade IOSEPHVS, 7. <hi>belli, cap.</hi> 18. of the deſtruction of the Temple, and of the moſt grieuous puniſhment of the Iewes, for their barbarous crueltie againſt our Sauiour Chriſt. The number of captiues was ninety and ſeuen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. The number of thoſe which were ſlaine and dead in the time of ſiege, was eleuen hundred thouſand. Idem 7. belli, c. 28. The famine ſo great, as they were brought to eate their owne and their childrens fleſh; to feede in ſinckes and channels. About forty thouſand of them had their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ripped vp, for the gould they were ſuppoſed to haue ſwallowed, &amp;c. and more had beene ſo barbarouſly entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted had not come forth a Prohibition. They were ſo vile, as thirtie of them were ſold for one peny. They haue beene ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and perſecuted of all Nations and peoples. Exceeding great numbers of them in one place or other continually murthered. They haue liued in intolerable ſlauery euer ſince the deſtruction of Ieruſalem, and euer ſhall. Ioſeph. 7. belli, cap. 28.</p>
                  <p>IVDAS hanged himſelfe with a halter. Matth. 26.</p>
                  <p>CAIPHAS being weary of his life, killeth himſelfe. Clem. Rom. Conſt. ap. 8. c. 1.</p>
                  <p>ANNAS alſo periſhed miſerably, as writeth Nicephor. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 40. Ioſephus and others.</p>
                  <p>HERODE ASCALOMITA, as hee ſought all meanes to deſtroy our Sauiour Chriſt, killed all the men children, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimatu &amp; infra,</hi> from two yeares old and vnder: ſo being moſt grieuouſly afflicted with a horrible diſeaſe, Ioſeph. an. lib. 17. cap. 17. &amp; cap. 8. ſought all meanes to deſtroy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, at laſt, his dolours being intolerable by Gods iuſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177554:8"/> judgement, he was extinct of a dropſie and corrupt humour, which ranne betwixt the skin and the fleſh, and eaten with wormes which crawled out of his skin. Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. li.</p>
                  <p>HERODE AGRIPPA, who put to death S. IAMES, and impriſoned S. PETER, was ſoone after in a publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly ſtriken from heauen with a moſt horrible diſeaſe, and died eaten vp with lice; yea his whole ſtocke, according to Ioſephus, which was moſt ample, within ſeuentie yeares was cleane rooted out.</p>
                  <p>HERODE ANTIPAS, which beheaded Saint IOHN Baptiſt, was firſt depriued of his dignitie, and with Herodias he was exiled to Lions in France for killing S. IOHN Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, as Authors Eccleſiaſticall affirme.</p>
                  <p>PONTIVS PILATVS was diuerſly puniſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſerts, and at laſt baniſhed to Vienna; he ſlew himſelfe. Euſeb. Caſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odor. Ado. in Chron.</p>
                  <p>NERO hated of all men for his crueltie, at laſt forſaken of his ſouldiers, and deſpairing euer to recouer his former ſtate, in great perplexitie arrayeth himſelfe in vile attire, fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away, and perceiuing hee was purſued, killed himſelfe. Sueton. 25. Dion. in Nerone.</p>
                  <p>DOMITIAN, for his barbarous crueltie, generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, was ſtabbed of Stephen, the ſteward of Flauia Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla: Sueton. Philoſt. trion. and others; his name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory was after aboliſhed. Macrob. Satur. lib. 1. cap. 12.</p>
                  <p>TRAIANVS, a cruell perſecutor of Chriſtians, is tepor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue beene poyſoned. See Baron.</p>
                  <p>HADRIANVS, like another Phalaris, raged againſt Chriſtians. The perſecution vnder him was ſo extreame, as Chriſtians were murthered at the cry of the common people. Neuertheleſſe in his time the Church was ſpread abroad far and neere. At laſt he was puniſhed with grieuous ſickneſſe, and ſo being very weary of his life, ſought often to kill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and finally procured one to ſlay him. See Baron.</p>
                  <p>SEVERVS, in regard of his cruelty exerciſed vpon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, was ſo puniſhed of God almightie, as he ſaw himſelfe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177554:8"/> moſt vnhappy in his children: for his ſonne Antoninus often attempted to ſlay him; and alſo he was not ignorant his ſon Geta ſhould be murthered as ſoone as Antoninus could get opportunitie to doe it. Antoninus ſlew Geta afterwards in his mothers lappe. Lege Baron. SEVERVS died, being conſumed with thought and griefe of minde. See Baron.</p>
                  <p>DECIVS, a moſt cruell perſecutor of Chriſtians, in the warre he made againſt the Gothes, together with his ſonne was extinct. Anno 2. Imper.</p>
                  <p>VALERIAN, as long as he fauoured Chriſtians, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed; but after he began to perſecute them, by the treaſon of Marrianus a Duke, he was deliuered ouer to Sapores, King of the Perſians, who euer after vſed VALERIAN for a foot-ſtoole to ſtand vpon when he went to horſe, at laſt hee commanded him to be flayed and ſalted. Baron.</p>
                  <p>CLAVDIVS raged moſt cruelly againſt Chriſtians, but in the third yeare of his Empire he died of the Peſtilence.</p>
                  <p>AVRELIAN, a ſeuere bloudie and cruell perſecutor, was beaten downe with thunder, and afterward killed of his owne ſubiects,</p>
                  <p>MAXIMIANVS, one of the cruelleſt perſecutors that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was, hanged himſelfe. Anno imper. Conſt. Panegyr. 4.</p>
                  <p>DIOCLETIAN, a like perſecutor, by the judgement of God was reſerued vnto the eleuenth yeare of Conſtantine, when he ſaw Chriſtian religion moſt flouriſhing, which hee with his fellow Maximian, ſought by all meanes they could to extinguiſh. At laſt, this yeare ſuſpecting ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorable death, it is ſaid he poyſoned himſelfe. Victor. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Euſeb. lib. 8. cap. vlt. Zozim. lib. 2. Zonor. Cedren, write of his miſerable death. See Baron. anno imper. Conſt. 11.</p>
                  <p>MAXENTIVS, a moſt cruell Tyrant, was drowned in Tiber. Euſeb. Zozimus and others.</p>
                  <p>IVLIAN the Apoſtata vſed all policie and arte he could (as formerly had done Diocletian and Maximian, to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Chriſtianitie; but all in vaine: Hee was ſlaine in the field againſt the Perſians; vncertainly by whom. S. Gregor,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177554:9"/> Nazian. orat. 2. in Iulian. <hi>miniſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> angelorum occiſum af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmat.</hi> See Baron. When hee died, hee filled his hand with bloud, and caſt it vp into the ayre, ſaying; <hi>viciſti Galilee,</hi> thou haſt vanquiſhed me, O Galilean, for ſo he called Chriſt Ieſus. Nicephor. 10. cap. 3. and alſo he ſaid <hi>ſaturare Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>VALENS, a moſt horrible perſecutor, making warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Gothes, was burned. See Baron, and others. Hee with his noble men fled into a poore cottage, which was burnt ouer his head, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>MAXIMINVS, a moſt bloudie perſecutor, was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne and put to flight by Licinius, and at laſt ſtricken with a moſt deadly and horrible diſeaſe, his eyes falling out of his head; he dieth miſerably, confeſſing himſelfe worthily puniſhed for his crueltie exerciſed vpon Chriſtians. Alſo, his children were put to a moſt reprochfull death: his ſtatuaes, titles, and other monuments were throwne downe, razed, aboliſhed. Conſtantini imper. anno 9.</p>
                  <p>HVNERICVS, King of the Vandals, perſecuted Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes moſt cruelly: he cauſed Catholikes tongues and right hands to be cut off, who, neuertheleſſe, by the helpe of God, did ſpeake as well afterwards as they did before. One of theſe, to wit, Reparatus a Subdeacon, pronounced eloquent Sermons without any difficultie; for which hee was highly reuerenced in Zeno, the Emperours Pallace; eſpecially Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina the Empreſſe honored him. See the Comp. of Baron. anno 484. fol. 425. There followeth (fol. 426<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) the miſerable death of this barbarous and cruell perſecutor: who, when he prepared to triumph ouer the Catholike faith, which he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thought to haue rooted out, periſhed moſt miſerably of wormes which crawled out of euery part of his bodie, the ſeuenth yeare of his raigne. Victor. lib. 3.</p>
                  <p>EVARICVS, King of the Gothes, ſpoileth France of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c. vpon deſire to propagate Arianiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee was a horrible perſecutor and enemie of Catholikes, like to Hune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus, as reporteth Eccleſiaſticall writers: being ſtricked from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177554:9"/> heauen, periſhed moſt miſerably, as writeth Turon. in the Hiſtory of France.</p>
                  <p>LEO ISAVRICVS, a moſt bloudy perſecutor, was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by an Earthquake out of this life, as writeth Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes.</p>
                  <p>CONSTANTINVS CAPRONYMVS, no leſſe cruell againſt Catholikes, was from heauen ſtricken with a plague and griefe in his thighes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which in Greeke is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſo died miſerably, crying out, and ſaying (being yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue) I am giuen ouer to vnquenchable fire. Theophanes and all other Greeke Authors witneſſeth the ſame. See Cedren. in Baron. anno 775.</p>
                  <p>LEO ARMENVS, a great enemie of the Catholike Church, was miſerably ſlaine neare the Altar, after hee had raigned ſeuen yeares and fiue moneths. And ſo periſh all which hate Sion.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>FOVRE MEMORABLE EXAMPLES FOLLOWING.</head>
                     <p>L. SEPTIMIVS PLAVTIANVS, from baſe ſtate, was aduanced to ſuch honor, as he was eſteemed little infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Emperour Seuerus himſelfe. This PLAVTIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVS thus exalted in ſuch grace with the Emperour, as the like hath ſcarcely euer beene ſeene, was honored with very many ſtatuaes, choſen to be father in law to Antoninus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, the ſonne of the Emperour. He married his daughter to Antoninus, with whom he gaue ſo much riches, and ſuch a dowrie, as had beene ſufficient to haue giuen with fiftie, (ſhould hee haue had ſo many to haue ſo highly preferred.) Hee was ſo horrible and cruell, as when hee was to goe any whither, ſome Sergeants or Virgiers were to take order that none ſhould be in his way, or preſume to looke vpon him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Of Chriſtians he was a moſt deadly enemie and cruell perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177554:10"/> with the ſpoiles of whom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after he had murthered and martyred them, he had infinitely enriched himſelfe. But loe, this cruell murtherer of Chriſtians fell from this ſoueraigne dignitie into extreame infelicity: in ſo much as he was (euen in the twelfth yeare of Seuerus Empire, become a wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full great laughing-ſtocke of humane felicitie, and a moſt dreadfull example of Gods ſeuere juſtice) he was (I ſay) put to a moſt miſerable death, by his ſonne in law, Antoninus, his body caſt into the ſtreet vnburied, his ſtatuaes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents pulled downe and defaced, his name ſcraped out, and aboliſhed. His ſonne and daughter were exiled, and at laſt in great miſery made away. So as that of the Pſalmiſt may be verified of him and ſuch like, <hi>Inimici domini mox vt honorificati fuerint, &amp; exaltati, deficientes quemadmedum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus deficient,</hi> Pſal. 36. The enemies of our Lord forthwith after they be raiſed to honor and exalted, vaniſhing away like ſmoake they ſhall vaniſh. See Baron. eſpecially the twelfth yeare of Seuerus Empire, where you ſhall finde all theſe, and much more of this horrible perſecutor.</p>
                     <p>EVTROPIVS, a man of ſeruile condition and lewde conuerſation, was ſo highly exalted vnder the Emperour Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadius, as he was of all other the greateſt Courtier, in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt grace and fauour with the Emperour. Hee was made Conſul, although generally hated of all people. He oppoſeth againſt Saint Iohn Chryſoſtome, Biſhop of Coſtantinople, and impugneth Eccleſiaſticall immunities, and liberties of the Church: Againſt which immunities and priuiledges of the Church in particular, that none flying to the Altar ſhould haue benefit of Sanctuary. But behold the puniſhment of this Tyrant: It pleaſed God that Gaynas being alienated from Arcadius, for his ſo much fauouring and aduancing this EVTROPIVS, as all in furie and rage, he made warre againſt the Emperour and brought him to this, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was glad to admit what conditions of peace Gaynas would offer. Amongſt which conditions, this was one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Emperour ſhould deliuer into his hands EVTROPIVS,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177554:10"/> that he might put him to what death it liked him. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on EVTROPIVS was depriued of all his places, dignities and riches, which were exceeding great: and ſo perceiuing his miſery, fled to the Church, layeth hold vpon Sanctuarie, and was for that time protected by Saint Chryſoſtome, who ſtood in the defence of the priuiledges of the Church, and would not permit the ſouldiers to take him from the Altar, before he had cauſed the Emperour to ſweare neither to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him into the hands of Gaynas, nor to put him to death. And although he had beene a great enemy of Saint Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and all the people cried to haue him made away. Yet Saint Chryſoſtome, in regard of the priuiledge, would not condeſcend, but with an eloquent oration diſſwadeth the people, and laboureth to ſaue him. So as it is to be noted, he that oppoſed himſelfe againſt this holy Biſhop, and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Church, had no other refuge, then to the ſame. Finally, being depriued of ſo many dignities, honors and riches, his name aboliſhed, his ſtatuaes, enſignes and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in all, both publike and priuate places defaced, he was baniſhed into Cyprus; from whence at the inſtance of Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he was ſent for, and beheaded. All this heere compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly touched, is ſet downe in Baronius at large, together with the Authors Eccleſiaſticall which write the ſame. This fellow was exalted and eleuated, as a Ceder of Libanus, but forthwith his place was not to be found. Pſal. 36.</p>
                     <p>CHRISAPHIVS, a moſt potent Courtier vnder Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius the Emperour, patronizeth Eutyches the damnable Heretike; perſecuteth and depoſeth Flauianus the holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke, turneth all vpſide downe: perſwadeth Theodoſius to fauour the Heretike<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to deſtroy the Catholike Biſhop. But God almightie juſtly puniſhed him. For Theodoſius fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out his treachery, repented hee had permitted him to protect this monſter, whereby ſuch a peſtilent ſect long after troubled the Church: and therefore he preſently depriueth this potent Courtier of all his places, and ſubſtance, and at laſt putteth him to death. Marcel. l. 14. c. 49. Niceph. Cedren. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Baron.</p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177554:11"/>
                     <p>BARDAS, who ruled all vnder Michael the third, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly perſecuted the Church, depoſed Ignatius the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke of Conſtantinople, a holy man, and contrary to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church, intruded Photius. It is wonderfull to conſider how hotly euery one of theſe, as wel the Emperour, who was a moſt beaſtly monſter, perſecuted Gods Saints, and all holies, as alſo the vſurper Photius, and the tyrant Bardas; what a horrible Schiſme they made. See all in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and other Authors, cited by him at large, for it is moſt memorable. Theſe monſters moſt grieuouſly afflicted the Church for ſome few yeares: but God almightie, after long patience powred forth his indignation againſt the factious and ſchiſmaticall Princes. Michael the third, which gaue himſelfe to nothing but his filthy pleaſures, as alſo Bardas, who ſwayed all. And firſt for Bardas, Curopalutes deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth his miſerable death, alſo Cedren, Glicas and Nicetas, doe the ſame almoſt in this manner. Bardas had a viſion, which was, viz. He ſaw Saint Peter the Prince of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and two terrible men aſſiſting, and Saint Peter being ſet, he ſaw Ignatius the Patriarke, whom he had expelled out of his See, lying at Saint Peters feete, crying; O Porter of the Kingdome of heauen, and the Rocke vpon which Chriſt hath built his Church, for as much as thou knoweſt how I haue beene iniured, comfort my old yeares, which haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered many euils. And Saint Peter ſaith to Ignatius, ſhew thy enemy which hath done thee ſo much wrong. <hi>Et Deus faciat vna cum tentatione prouentum,</hi> and God will make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with temptation iſſue. And Ignatius turning to me, pointed me out with his right hand. This Bardas is he, who all aboue others hath offended and iniured me, neither yet ceaſeth more and more to afflict me. Then Saint Peter ſaid to him that aſſiſted on the right hand, take away this execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and curſed Bardas out of the Church, and preſently cut him in peeces, and therefore I was led to death. All this Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſaw in a viſion: and moreouer, hee ſaw him ſhake his head againſt the Emperour, ſaying, <hi>Impie ſili expecta parum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177554:11"/> This terrible viſion Bardas (himſelfe all affrighted, and with teares) reported to Philotheus his faithfull friend. Who notwithſtanding all this, ceaſed not more grieuouſly to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the holy Patriarke Ignatius for three moneths after; at the end of which time followed the execution of this viſion. When as Bardas, with the Emperour and his armie went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Crete, where being ſuſpected of treaſon, the Emperour commanded him to be hacked in peeces. Now for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour himſelfe, he tooke one Baſilius, a Macedonian, to be his conſort. This Baſilius created Emperour, ſtudying to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Michael from his wicked and deteſtable manners and conuerſation, procured Michael to hate him: in ſo much as he perceiued the Emperour Michael ſought to deſtroy and make him away, as hee had done Bardas; and therefore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſiring to kill, then to be killed, contriueth preſently the death of the beaſtly monſter: which act, though it was not lawfull, yet was the perſecutor juſtly puniſhed for his crueltie againſt Gods Church. Zonoras, Nicetas and others. This Baſil ſendeth Embaſſadors to the Pope, reſtoreth peace to the Church, expulſeth Photius the vſurper from the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archall See, and reſtoreth the true Biſhop Ignatius into the ſame, to the great joy and exultation of all people. Many more like examples might be added to theſe, but theſe are moſt notorious.</p>
                     <p>As God almightie hath a ſpeciall prouidence ouer his Church in the law of grace, as it ſhall neuer be deſtroyed by any impugnation of what enemies ſoeuer, but ſhall ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine glorious, though neuer ſo much perſecuted by tyrants; which tyrants, and enemies of Gods Church, often periſh miſerably euen in this world, beſides the eternall miſeries they fall into after this life, if they die impenitent. So is it to be noted, that the ſame God almightie had alſo a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull care ouer his Kingdome and people, euen in the old Teſtament; and ſuch as perſecuted them, we may ſee by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples to what miſerable confuſion they fell at laſt.</p>
                     <p>PHARAO with all his hoaſt was drowned in the red ſea.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177554:12"/>
                     <p>AMAN which had contriued the meanes to put to death, and maſſacre all Gods choſen people vnder Aſſuerus, was hanged vpon a gibbet fifty cubits high, which he had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Mardocheus. Heſt. 7.</p>
                     <p>IESABEL, which ſlew Gods Prophets, was throwne downe out of a window, killed with the fall, and eaten of dogs. 4. King. 9.</p>
                     <p>ANTIOCHVS moſt grieuouſly and extreamely perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and afflicted Gods people, as we reade in the 2. of the Machabees: but as it is in the ninth chapter of the ſaid book; God which ſeeth all, ſtrake him with an incurable and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible plague. Hee threatned to deſtroy Ieruſalem and all the people, and God almightie, preſently vpon it, laid his heauy hand vpon him. Reade the ninth chapter of the ſecond book, and you ſhall ſee the miſerable end of this moſt proud and cruel enemie of God and his Kingdom. He could not go, but was carried: his dolours and anguiſh was intolerable, and that by the juſt judgement of God, for he had moſt vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully tortured and afflicted Gods people; wormes crawled out of his body, and the horrible ſtincke thereof annoyed his whole armie: who a little before was ſo proud and inſolent, as he thought he could reach the ſtarres of heauen: him no man can now carry, or come neere, for intolerable ſtincke. This cruel homicide, and blaſphemous wretch miſerably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his life in his peregrination. See more in the Machabees.</p>
                     <p>In the fourth booke of Kings, and the nineteenth chapter, you may ſee recorded the miſerable doſtruction of Sennache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib and his whole armie, which had beſieged Hieruſalem, blaſphemed God, and threatned to deſtroy the Citie, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly King Ezechias, and all his people. But God almightie, who knoweth how to deliuer his faithfull people, ſent his Angell into the tents of the Aſſirians, which ſlew a hundreth and eightie fiue thouſand of them in their tents, after which, Sennacherib returned into his owne countrie, where he was ſlaine of Adramelach and Saraſar his owne ſonnes. Reade the ſeuen and thirtieth chapter of Iſal.</p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:177554:12"/>
                     <p>It is alſo worthy to be noted, that ſuch as diuided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by any Schiſme in the old Law, were moſt ſeuerely puniſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as for example, Chore, Dathan and Abiron, and their complices, to the number of foureteene thouſand and ſeuen hundreth men, beſides many others that periſhed in the ſedition before. Theſe rebelled againſt Moſes their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Superiour.</p>
                     <p>IEROBOAM, who vpon a diuelliſh policie drew the people from the true worſhip and ſeruice of God to Idolatry and Schiſme, God almightie ſo puniſhed him, as he left not one of his ſeed to piſſe againſt a wall. 3. King. 14. So as wee may plainly ſee there is no wiſdome, no prudence, no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell againſt God. Theſe Politicks take a wrong courſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance and continue their ſtates and families, for <hi>Niſi Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus aedificauerit domum, &amp;c.</hi> Vnleſſe our Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it, Pſal. 126. for theſe Houſes, Kingdomes and States that are founded by ſuch Machieuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian policies, neuer continue long, as appeareth moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, Pſal. 16. <hi>Noli <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mulari in malignantibus, ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Zelaueris facientes iniquitatem, &amp;c.</hi> Reade the whole Pſalme, wherein it is ſaid, the impious and wicked enemies of God ſhall wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away as graſſe, vaniſh as ſmoke, their ſeed and very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques ſhall periſh, though for a while they flouriſh neuer ſo much, and be neuer ſo highly exalted, encreaſed and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the world; yet ſhall they come in ſhort time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and deſtruction.</p>
                     <p>As God almighty dealt with IEROBOAM, Author of that notorious Schiſme and diuiſion, ſo likewiſe did hee to Baaza, Zamri and Achab, Kings of Iſrael, for that (ſaith the third booke of Kings) they walked in the wayes of Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am: that is, becauſe they continued the Schiſme, and did not reduce the Iſraelites to the true worſhip and ſeruice of God. You ſhal find that of all thoſe, God almighty left not one to piſſe againſt a wall, for this is the phraſe of Scripture in that place. Theſe are dreadfull examples of Gods ſeuere ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt the Authors, fauourers and maintainers of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177554:13"/> Schiſme againſt God, his Church and Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>To theſe might be added a great many more, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where occurre in the old Teſtament. Reade Pſalme 82. where you ſhall ſee a great number of Kings and Princes which ſought to deſtroy Gods people, to come to miſerable ends. Theſe ſeeking to ouerthrow Gods Kingdome, doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, but they incurre his heauy wrath and indignation to their owne vtter ruine, confuſion, and extirpation.</p>
                     <p>Of all this before written, wee may gather that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie hath a ſingular prouidence ouer his Church and Kingdome, he neither ſlumbreth nor ſleepeth which keepeth Iſrael. Pſal. 120. Tyrants, perſecutors and fooliſh people may oppoſe themſelues againſt it, ſeeke to extinguiſh it; but all in vaine. <hi>Qui haebitat in coelis irridebit eos, &amp; Dominus ſubſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabit eos,</hi> He that dwelleth in the heauen will laugh them to ſcorne, &amp;c. Pſal. 2. God almightie doth gratiouſly protect his Church, and though he ſuffer it to be mightily impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet <hi>faciet cum tentatione prouentum,</hi> hee will make with temptation iſſue. The Catholike Church, and Kingdome of our Sauiour Chriſt, hath by this meanes beene maruailouſly encreaſed and propagated, as all Eccleſiaſticall writers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly teſtifie; as contrariwiſe the enemies thereof haue moſt miſerably periſhed, and come to confuſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>CERTAINE MEMORABLE EXAMPLES OF GODS SEVERE REVENGE AGAINST ſuch as were rebellious and iniurious to Prieſts <hi>of the olde Law.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1 OF CHORE, DATHAN and ABIRON, we haue ſpoken before, how themſelues, and al that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vnto them, was ſwallowed vp of the earth. Numb. 16.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 MARIA the ſiſter of MOSES, for murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, was puniſhed with a leproſie. Num. 12.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 SAVL, becauſe he obeyed not Samuel the Prophet, loſt his Kingdome. 1. King. 31.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177554:13"/>4 ACHAB, for contemning the Prophet Micheas, and caſt him into priſon, was ſlaine in warre, 3. King. 22. and Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, the ſonne of Achab, and all his progeny were ſlaine by Iehu. That I may reuenge (ſaith the Prophet vnto Iehu) the bloud of my ſeruants the Prophets, and the bloud of all the ſeruants of our Lord, from the hand of Ieſabel. 4. King. 9.</p>
                     <p>IOAS, who ſlew Zachary the Prieſt and Prophet in the porch of the houſe of God, was puniſhed moſt grieuouſly. Paralip. 24. For the yeare following the Syrians came into Iudea and Ieruſalem, and ſlew all the Princes of the people, and ſent all the prey vnto the King of Syria into Damaſco: and whereas there came but a ſmall number of the Syrians, yet God deliuered an infinite multitude into their hands, and Ioas they puniſhed with all ignominy and reproch, and left him in great ſicknes and miſery: And his owne ſeruants roſe vp againſt him, to reuenge the bloud of the ſonne of Ioiad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Prieſt, and they ſlew him in his bed.</p>
                     <p>AMASIAS, King of Iuda, becauſe hee contemned the Prophet of God, &amp;c. was deliuered into the hands of Ioas King of Iſrael, being ſpoiled of all he had, and afterwards ſlaine of his owne ſeruants. 2. Paralip. 25.</p>
                     <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>IAS his ſon, becauſe he vſurped Prieſtly function and authority, was ſtricken with a leproſie, 2. Paral. 26. And that which Chriſt ſpake in the Goſpell (the bloud of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, from the bloud of Abel the Iuſt, vnto the bloud of Zacharie the Prophet, ſhall be required at your hands, Luk. 11.) hath terribly expreſſed this reuenge of almightie God, for the diſperſion of the Iewes throughout all the whole world vntill this day, is nothing elſe but the juſt reuenge of almightie God for the bloud of Chriſt, and all the Prophets.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177554:14"/>
                     <head>EXAMPLES OF GODS SEVERE PV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISHMENTS AGAINST SVCH AS CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne Biſhops and Prieſts.</head>
                     <p>BY many example precedent, as alſo by theſe enſuing, collected out of Hiſtories Eccleſiaſticall and prophane, it may appeare how Emperours, Kings and Princes, which would not be obedient children to Gods Church, but perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the ſame, haue come to miſerable ends.</p>
                     <p>CONSTANTIVS fauouring the Arians, after hee had baniſhed Liberius Pope, Athanaſius alſo Biſhop of Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, and many other Catholike Biſhops, and had arrogated and taken to himſelfe, to heare and know all cauſes Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall (as at large ſheweth Saint Athanaſius, ep. ad. Sol. v. ag. whileſt he perſecuted Iulian, &amp;c. ended his life in an obſcure place, and in great torment of conſcience. As at large deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Ammian. Marcellin. l. 22. hiſt.</p>
                     <p>VALENS, who baniſhed the Catholikes into obſcure places, and vſed all rigour and ſeueritie againſt them, was puniſhed with like meaſure himſelfe, with his Princes in the warre againſt the Gothes, flying into an old houſe, was with all his Princes burned, and the houſe ouer their heads. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian. Marcel. l. 31. This Emperour caſt the holy religious man Iſacius into priſon, as Achab did Micheas the Prophet.</p>
                     <p>VALENTINIAN the yonger, who many wayes vexed Saint Ambroſe, to make him yeeld a Church vnto the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, and threatned to exile him, was hanged by his owne ſeruants ignominiouſly ſhortly after.</p>
                     <p>ANASTATIVS the Emperour excommunicated of Pope Gelaſius, was an extreame perſecutor, as well of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops as of Monkes, and religious perſons, was killed with lightning and fire from heauen.</p>
                     <p>MAVRITIVS the Emperour, who perſecuted S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory the Great, was ſlaine of a common ſouldier, his wife and all his children before put to death in his owne ſight, and ſo cried, <hi>Iuſtus es Domine, &amp; rectum iudicium tuum.</hi> Thou
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177554:14"/> art juſt, O Lord, and righteous is thy judgement. Blondus lib. 3. Decad. 1.</p>
                     <p>CONSTANS, the Nephew of Heraclius baniſhed Pope Martine, for which he was hated of all his ſubiects, ſaith Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noras, and ſo leauing Conſtantinople, liued in Cicely, and there was killed in the Bathe of his owne people about him. Paul. Diac. lib. 18.</p>
                     <p>MICHAEL Emperour, the ſonne of Theophilus, which behaued himſelfe proudly againſt Pope Nicholas the firſt, and moſt iniuriouſly depoſed Ignatius the Patriarch of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople: when he went drunke to bed one night, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at his bed ſide, was ſlaine of his owne domeſticals, Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Annal. tom. 3. in Conſtante &amp; Michaele.</p>
                     <p>CONSTANTINVS PROGNATVS, the ſon of Leo Iſauricus, a moſt cruell perſecutor of the Catholike Clergie, was ſtricken with fire from heauen, and ſo died blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. Sigeb. ad Ann. 778.</p>
                     <p>Theſe wonderfull and notable judgements of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, happened to the greateſt Princes in the Eaſt, which perſecuted Chriſt Ieſus in his Vicars, &amp;c. And there haue beene no leſſe renowned in the Weſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>PERSECVTORS IN THE WEST CHVRCH.</head>
                     <p>HENRY the fourth, the firſt of the Weſterne Emperours, which oppoſed himſelfe againſt the Church: after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iniuries offered thereunto, being excommunicate by Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory the 7. was depriued of his Empire by his owne ſonne, and at laſt forſaken of all, died in great calamitie in exile, out of the limits of the Empire. Nauclerus, vol. 3. gener. 37.</p>
                     <p>FREDERICVS BARBAROSSA, which for many years perſecuted the Church of God, very rebellious and proud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the See Apoſtolike: when he was bathing himſelfe in a riuer for his pleaſure in Cilicia, was drowned of a ſodaine, and ſo ended. Naucl. gen. 40.</p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177554:15"/>
                     <p>OTHO the fourth, after exceeding great iniuries done to the Church throughout all Italy, being aſſaulted in warre, and put to flight by Philip the French King in low Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; a little after died a priuate man in Saxony. Staplet. in prompt. mor. in dom. paſſ. text. 4.</p>
                     <p>FREDERICVS the ſecond, a moſt cruell perſecutor, not onely of the See Apoſtolique, but of all the Clergie throughout the whole Empire, excommunicated by Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the fourth, was ſlaine of his baſtard ſonne Manfrede in Apulia, as ſome write, poyſoned, as others report, hanged: and all his race following the ſteps of their wicked father, came to the like miſerable end. His eldeſt ſonne Conradus, for like cauſe excommunicated by Innocent the forth, was killed by the ſame Manfrede in Apulia. And the ſame Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frede entring vpon the Kingdomes of Apulia and Sicilia, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe a cruell enemie of the Church, excommunicated by Alexander the fourth, was vanquiſhed and put to flight by Charles, brother to the King of France, whom Vrbane the fourth declared King of Sicilia and Apulia.</p>
                     <p>CONRADINVS, ſonne to the ſaid Conrade, vanquiſhed by the ſaid Charles, was put to death. And Eutius the other ſon of Frederick the ſecond, after many warres made againſt the Church, being taken of the Bononians, was committed to perpetuall impriſonment; and ſo all the race and ſtock of the ſacrilegious Emperour, great in number and power, in ſhort time extinct, left to poſteritie an example of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked rebellions againſt God and his Church.</p>
                     <p>LEWES the fourth Emperour, twice excommunicate by the See Apoſtolike, in whoſe defence againſt the immunities and priuiledges of the Church of Rome, thoſe Poets and Rhetoritians for this cauſe infamous, Petrarcha, Dantes, Marſilius, and Io. Occhamus Schoole-man, write ſo many things: God almightie judgeing this cauſe; when he was a hunting, taken ſodainly with a palſey of all his members, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from his horſe, died ſodainly.</p>
                     <p>Memorable it is, which Nicephorus writeth of Narciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177554:15"/> Biſhop of Hieruſalem. Three maleuolous perſons falſely accuſed this holy Biſhop, wiſhing euill to themſelues if they dealt falſely: The firſt, that he would be burnt: The ſecond, that he ſhould die of the falling euill, or ſome other deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſeaſe: The third wiſhed his eyes out of his head. But Gods diuine reuenge not ſleeping, the firſt with al his houſe, kinsfolkes and ſubſtance, was burnt by one ſparke that fell from a candle: The ſecond was taken with a moſt grieuous diſeaſe, which entred vpon his whole body: The third forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with confeſſeth the deceitfull dealing, and fraudulent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, ceaſed not to weepe and ſhed teares, vntill he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with his teares to loſe the ſtrength and ſight of his eyes. Theſe torments of few, may be examples for all.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE VNHAPPY ENDS OF ARCH-HERETICKES.</head>
                     <p>ALthough God almighty puniſheth and ſcourgeth his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and children; yet alwayes at laſt he caſteth the rod into the fire: Deut. 32. <hi>Laudate Gentes populum eius, quia ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem ſeruorum ſuorum vlciſcetur, &amp; vindictam retribuet in hoſtes eorum.</hi> You Gentiles praiſe his people, becauſe he will reuenge the bloud of his ſeruants, and will repay vengeance vpon their enemies.</p>
                     <p>This thing is manifeſt by that which is aboue-written. And it may further appeare by the vnhappy and miſerable ends of Apoſtataes and Arch-heretiques. As firſt of SIMON MAGVS, when he began to flie, he was throwne downe by the prayers of Saint Peter, brake his legges, and a little after died with great ignominy. Hegeſip. lib. 3. cap. 2. de excid. Hieroſol. &amp; Arnob. lib. 2. contra Gentes.</p>
                     <p>MANICHAEVS was flayed aliue by the King of Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not for his Hereſie, or his faith and religion; but for that taking in hand to cure the Kings ſonne, he killed him. Epiphan. haereſ. 66.</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177554:16"/>
                     <p>MONTANVS, THEODORVS, and their propheteſſes hanged themſelues. Euſeb. lib. 5. hiſt. cap. 16.</p>
                     <p>Certaine Donatiſtes, when they did caſt the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Euchariſt to the dogs, were of the ſame dogs torne in peeces. Optat. lib. 2. contra Parmenianum.</p>
                     <p>ARIVS, when hee was going to the Church with great pompe, was ſodainly troubled with ache in his belly, and ſo forced to diuert a priuy, or houſe of office, and there toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his excrements, auoided both his entrailes and his life. Witneſſe S. Athanaſius Orat. 1. contra Arianos, &amp; Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin. lib. 10. hiſtor. cap. 13.</p>
                     <p>IVLIAN the Apoſtata was ſlaine from heauen miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly: he was neuer buried, but (as ſaith S. Gregory Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen in his Oration, made in praiſe of S. Athanaſius, neere the end) the earth of it ſelfe opened, and ſwallowed him vp.</p>
                     <p>VALFNS the Arian, which ſucceeded Iulian in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Catholikes, was burned aliue by the Gothes, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were Arians. Ruffin. lib. 2. hiſt. cap. 13.</p>
                     <p>NESTORIVS periſhed moſt miſerably, his tongue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eaten and conſumed with wormes. Euag. lib. 1. hiſt. c. 7.</p>
                     <p>ANASTATIVS the Emperour, a fauourer of the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chian Heretikes, was killed with lightning, as write Cedro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus and Paul the Deacon, in his life.</p>
                     <p>LEO ICONOMACHVS, that is, Image-breaker, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſacred Images in the open market place of Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople. Preſently after which fact, the peſtilence conſumed three hundred thouſand people in Conſtantinople. See the Chronicle of Matth. Palmer. Anno DCC. XLI.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>TO OMIT MANY OTHERS, AND TO ASCEND TO THE MONSTERS of our age.</head>
                     <p>LVTHER died ſodainly, for hauing ſupped very delicately and pleaſantly, being in perfect health, and hauing deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177554:16"/> all his company with merry conceits; the ſame night he died. Coclaeus in vita Lutheri.</p>
                     <p>ZVINGLIVS was ſlaine in war, which he made againſt Catholikes, and a little after, his brother Oecolampadius go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed in good health, one night, was found dead by his wife in the morning. Coclaeus in act. Luth. an. 1531.</p>
                     <p>ANDREAS CAROLOSTADIVS, the Miniſters of Baſil write to haue been killed of a Diuell, in their Epiſtle of the death of Caroloſtadius.</p>
                     <p>IOANNES CALVINVS was eaten and conſumed of wormes, and died as did Antiochus, Hunery, Maximinus, &amp;c. as witneſſeth Hieronymus Bolſecus in his life, who alſo addeth that the Arch-heretique died blaſpheming, curſing, and inuocating Diuels. This Heretique, that beſides his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereſies, denied prayer to Saints, at his death prayeth vnto Diuels.</p>
                     <p>To all theſe former examples, we might adde infinit more of notorious perſecutors, and enemies of Gods Church, which all came to miſerable ends: and ſo ſhall all others come to confuſion which hate Sion, which oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt Gods Church and Kingdome, which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath built vpon a firme Rocke, and therefore no ſtormes, windes or tempeſts can ouerthrow it. Matth. 16. 18. <hi>Port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> inferi non praeualebunt aduerſus eam.</hi> The gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile againſt it, as hath promiſed our Sauiour. Whatſoeuer the diuell can doe by Tyrants, Heretickes, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other aduerſaries againſt this Church, it ſtandeth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable, <hi>Deus fundauit eam in aeternum.</hi> God hath founded it for euer, Pſal. 47. Saint Auguſtine expoundeth this of the Church of God. This Church is Gods Kingdome, whereof it is ſaid, Luk. 1. <hi>&amp; Regni eius non erit finis,</hi> and of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall be no end. Of this Kingdome it is ſaid, Dan. 2. <hi>Iu diebus autem regnorum eorum, ſuſcitabit Deus coeli regnum, quod in aeternum non diſſipabitur, &amp; regnum eius alteri populo non tradetur, comminuet &amp; conſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t vniuerſa regna haec, &amp; ipſum ſtabit in aeternum.</hi> This Kingdome then of God, his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177554:17"/> Church, ſhall ſtand and continue for euer. No tyrannie nor perſecution can deſtroy this Church, no it cannot dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, but rather encreaſe it, as euidently hath beene ſeene in all ages. And this is that Saint Leo writeth, Ser. 1. <hi>de Petro &amp; Paulo,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Non minuitur perſecutionibus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, ſed augetur, &amp; ſemper dominicus ager ſegete ditiori veſtitur, dum grana quae ſingula cadunt, multiplicata naſeuntur.</hi> The Church is not diminiſhed by perſecution, but increaſed, and alwaies our Lords field is clothed with richer graine, whileſt the graine, which one by one doe fall into the ground, doe ſpring vp multiplied.</p>
                     <p>And although God almighty ſometime leaueth ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular country and people for hereſie and ſinne; yet he will ſtill haue his Church, he wil raiſe others, and call other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as we may ſee after the fall of the Church in Africk, and ſome parts of the Eaſt, many other goodly Kingdomes and Prouinces were preſently conuerted to the faith of Chriſt, heere in the Weſt-Church, as in Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories may cleerely be ſeene. And now ſince the fall of our Countrey, and ſome other places neere vnto vs, from the Catholike faith, wee know that innumerable people in Africk, in the Eaſt and Weſt Indies are conuerted to this ſame Catholike Church, and true faith of Chriſt: whereby wee ſee verified that dreadfull threate of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Auferetur a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis regnum Dei, &amp; dabitur genti facienti fructus eius.</hi> This Kingdome, that is, the preaching of the Goſpell, is taken from vs, becauſe we brought not forth the fruits of it, and ſquared not our liues according to the rules thereof. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath take from vs our true Teachers, and lawfull Paſtors, hauing lawfull miſſion and vocation, without which none euer preached or taught Catholike truth, but were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of ſeditious doctrine and pernicious hereſie, as we now ſee by lamentable experience in theſe parts of Chriſtendom.</p>
                     <p>This conſidered, I hope all good Catholikes and ſeruants of Chriſt; which are in the lap of the Catholike Church, will be of good comfort, cleaue vnto this Rocke, the piller and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177554:17"/> foundation of truth, as the Apoſtle calleth it. In ſo doing they ſhall neuer be drowned in the waues of Hereſie and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie. If ſome Catholikes, either out of feare of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or loſſe of their temporalties, fall from this Church, God almightie will call others, yea euen Puritanes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeduced ſoules. Theſe will he call to the knowledge of his truth, theſe will he gather into his Church; and theſe once ſeeing what a ſingular benediction, what a ſoueraigne benefit it is, to bee within the houſe of God, which is his Church, will for euer laude and praiſe his holy name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Thoſe will ſay with the royall Prophet, Pſal. 83. <hi>Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or eſt dies vna in atrijs tuis ſuper millia.</hi> Better is one day in thy Courts aboue a thouſand, and <hi>beati qui habitant in dome tua Domine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in ſaecula ſaeculorum laudabunt te:</hi> bleſſed are they which dwell in thy houſe, O Lord; for euer and euer they will praiſe thee: and <hi>Elegi abiectus eſſe, &amp;c.</hi> I had rather be an abiect in the houſe of our Lord, then to dwell in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of ſinners. And therefore vnderſtanding the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this benefit, they will pray with the ſame holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Pſal. 23. <hi>Vnam petij a domino hanc requiram vt in habitem in domo domini omnibus diebus vitae meae.</hi> One thing haue I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought of our Lord; and this will I aske againe, that I may dwell in the houſe of our Lord all the dayes of my life. Out of this houſe, that is, the Catholike Church, there is no meanes of ſaluation, neither by preaching, nor by Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; out of this Church no remiſſion of ſinnes, out of this Church no good worke can be meritorious of euerlaſting life: Whoſoeuer falleth out of this Church, as he cannot merite by any good worke of prayer, faſting, or almes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not in ſtate of grace; ſo he loſeth the merite of all his former good workes, though neuer ſo many. What loſſe can euer be comparable to this? Whoſoeuer falleth out of this Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ioſeth the communion of Saints, ſetteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe out of Gods grace, ſauour, and protection out of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trociny of Angels and Saints; ſuch cannot be Gods children, but his enemies, ſuch can receiue no influence of Gods grace,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177554:18"/> no ſanctification, no juſtification, no comfort of the holy Ghoſt: ſuch can haue no peace or quiet of conſcience: ſuch as be out of Gods Church, cannot preſume God will heare their prayers, according to that, Pſal. 65. <hi>Iniquitatem ſi aspexi in corde meo, non exaudiet deus:</hi> Such as are not capable of any Sacrament, and conſequently, not of ſaluation: ſuch as die out of this Church, without doubt periſh euerlaſtingly.</p>
                     <p>If then, as I ſaid before, Catholikes doe not weigh theſe things, but for feare of temporall loſſes, or diſcommoditie, fall out of this Church, God almightie will call vnto him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are yet ſeduced and blinded with hereſie and ſinne. Theſe after their calling to ſo great grace, after their ſoules and hearts are illuminated, will take wonderfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in ſo inexplicable a benefit, as this of their vocation and juſtification. Theſe will be feruent and deuout in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, theſe wil neuer ceaſe to laude and praiſe his holy name: theſe will neuer ſuffer themſelues to be ſeperated from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God againe: theſe will contemne life, goods, friends, lands and all, for this ineſtimable Iewell: theſe like to the Primitiue Chriſtians, wil neuer be daunted with perſecution, but will rejoyce in it, both in reſpect of grace, Gods greateſt treaſure they receiue in this life, and glory, that moſt ample reward they expect in the next world.</p>
                     <p>And therefore to conclude, let none be diſcouraged with feare of perſecution or troubles: for whatſoeuer thou ſhalt loſe in this life, thou ſhalt receiue it euen heere an hundred fould, and alſo a crowne of glory in the Kingdom of heauen. And therfore I ſay with S. Cyprian, <hi>Non vereamur occidi quos conſtat cum occidimur coronari.</hi> Let vs not feare to be murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whom when we are murdered, certain it is we are crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. We ſhould be ſo far from being terrified with perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as we ſhould exceedingly reioyce in it: <hi>Gaudete &amp; exulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>niam merces v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtra copioſa eſt in coelis.</hi> be glad and reioyce, for your reward is very great in heauen. To ſuffer perſecution willingly and joyfully for Chriſts cauſe, for the profeſſion of the Catholike faith, is our glory: and the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177554:18"/> Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Abſit mihi gloriari niſi in Cruce Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti.</hi> God forbid I ſhould glory in any thing, but in the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. The Croſſe is the moſt precious Iewell of our Sauiour Chriſt: and of this Iewell he alwaies giueth the greateſt portions to his deareſt friends. Let vs therefore amids our greateſt croſſes and tribulations be of good comfort; there is no better ſigne of our election and predeſtination, then (liuing in Gods grace and fauour, and keeping our ſelues in the vnity and obedience of our holy Mother the Catholike Church) to be diuers wayes afflicted and perſecuted, to be robbed and ſpoiled, belied and ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the enemies of Gods eternall truth. Let vs not ſuffer for theft, for murther, for other criminall matters, but if it be for Catholike religion, for obedience to our lawfull Paſtors, and ſpirituall guides, which doe watch ouer vs, as bound to render an account for our ſoules, according to the Apoſtle, Hebr. 13. 17. <hi>Obedite praepoſitis veſtris, &amp;c.</hi> Let vs not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, but eſteeme our ſelues euen bleſſed in this life, as our Sauiour pronounceth of vs. And the more we ſhall ſuffer for ſo glorious a cauſe, ſo much more happy we ſhall be: for there is no proportion betwixt our preſent ſufferings, and the future rewards. <hi>Non ſunt condigne paſsiones huius temporis ad futuram gloriam.</hi> The paſſions of this time are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne to the glory to come, that ſhall be reuealed in vs. Rom. 8. 18. Let vs then reioyce in tribulation, and nothing doubt but that our mercifull Lord who ſends it, will likewiſe ſend comfort with it. 2. Cor. 17. <hi>Sicut ſocij eſt is paſsionum, ſic eritis &amp; conſolationis in Chriſto Ieſu Domino noſtro.</hi> As you are fellowes of his paſſions, ſo alſo ſhall you be of conſolation in Chriſt Ieſus, &amp;c. And againe <hi>Sicut abundant paſſionis Chriſti in nobis: ita &amp; per Chriſtum abundat conſolatio noſtra.</hi> As the paſſions of Chriſt abound in vs, ſo alſo by Chriſt aboundeth our conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as moſt excellently writeth the Apoſtle Saint Paul, 2. Cor. 1. 5. To make an end, let vs reioyce in tribulation, at leaſt eſteeme it all joy when we fall into diuers temptations, as exhorteth bleſſed Saint Iames, chap. 1. 2. But if wee doe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177554:19"/> finde in our ſelues this imperfection, that we cannot reioyce in croſſes and troubles, neither yet haue that high eſteeme of it, as we ought, at leaſt let vs diſpoſe our ſelues to patience, for ſuch as loſe patience, as out of feare fall away: the Angel, or rather our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith in the Apocalyps, Their part ſhall be in the burning lake, Apocal. 31. 8. And that which may moſt encourage vs, is that comfortable aſſertion of our Sauiour Chriſt, often repeated in the Apocalyps, <hi>Qui vicerit dabo ei edere Mannae abſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nditum, &amp;c.</hi> He that ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, I will giue him to eate hidden Manna. <hi>Qui vicerit dabo ei edere de ligno vitae quod eſt in Paradiſo.</hi> Hee that ſhall ouercome, I will giue him to eate of the tree of life, which is in Paradiſe. Happy are they that ſhall feed of this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread, and that ſhall eate of this delicate fruite, for they ſhall liue for euer.</p>
                     <p>This which hath been ſaid may not only be of great force to confirme the obedient, and reſolute children of Gods Church, but alſo may auaile much to confound ſuch as liue in Schiſme, and participate with Heretikes in their execrable ſeruice and Sacraments, contrary to their conſciences. Whom, beſides theſe former points, I beſeech in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, to reflect vpon the vncertainty of this life, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of all earthly things; vpon Gods ſeuere judgements executed vpon rebellious and ſchiſmaticall people; vpon the foure laſt things, to wit, Death, Iudgement, Heauen and Hell: vpon the conſtancie of innumerable moſt glorious Martyrs of either ſexe, &amp;c. And they cannot, conſidering theſe things with ſerious attention, they cannot poſſibly (I ſay) continue longer in Schiſme, but with all ſpeed recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile themſelues to almightie God and his Church. And that this (I ſay) may take better effect with them. I will conclude with thoſe two excellent ſayings of Saint Auguſtine, moſt worthy to be noted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firmiſſime tene &amp; nullatenus dubites non ſolum omnes Paganos ſed etiam Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>os, Haereticos<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Schiſm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, qui extra Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Catholicam praeſentem fini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>t vitam in ignem aeternum ituro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177554:19"/> qui paratus eſt Diabolo &amp; Angelis eius. B. Auguſt: lib. de fide ad Petrum.</hi> Hould moſt firmely, and in no wiſe doubt, that not only all Pagans, but alſo all Iewes, Heretickes and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, which out of the Catholike Church end this preſent life, ſhall goe into euerlaſting fire, which is prepared for the Diuell and his Angels. And the other:</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Firmiſſime tene &amp; nullatenus dubites quemlibet haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſchiſmaticum in nomine Patris &amp; Filij &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti baptizatum, ſi Eccleſiae Catholicae non fuerit aggregatus, quantaſcun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> eleemoſynas fecerit, etſi pro Chriſti nomine etiam ſanguinem fuderit, nullatenus poſſe ſaluari: Omni enim homini qui Eccleſiae non tenet vnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> baptiſmus, ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> eleemoſyna quantumlibet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſa, ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> mors pro Chriſti nomine ſuſcepta proficere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ad ſalutem, quamdiu in eo haeretica, vel ſchiſmatica prauitas perſeuerat, quae ducit ad mortem.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hould moſt firmely, and no waies doubt, that euery He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick and Schiſmaticke baptiſed in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, if he be not joyned to Gods Church, how great almes ſoeuer hee giue, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſhed his bloud for Chriſts ſake, can no wayes bee ſaued: for euery man that holdeth not the vnitie of the Church, neither baptiſme nor almes, although neuer ſo great, neither death ſuffered for Chriſts cauſe, can profit vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as long as hereticall lewdneſſe perſeuereth in him, which leadeth vnto death.</p>
                     <p>Finally, for ſuch as are within the lappe of the Catholike Church, I beſeech them to ſquare their liues according to the precepts and rules of Catholike religion, which induce to holines and perfection of life; and I ſay vnto them with the Apoſtle. <hi>Abijciamus opera tenebrarum, &amp; induamur arma lucis, ſicut in die honeſte ambulemus, non in comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſationibus, &amp; ebri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tatibus: non in cubilibus &amp; impudicitijs: non in contentione, &amp; aemulatione, ſed induimini Ieſum Chriſtum.</hi> Let vs caſt away the workes of darknes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and put on the armour of light, let vs walke honeſtly as in the day time, not in banquetting and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177554:20"/> drunkenneſſe, not in champering and immundicities, not in contention and emulation, but doe you on our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Rom. 13. It is not enough to be in the Catholike Church, vnleſſe we liue according to the rules of our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion. If we giue our ſelues to ſenſuality and volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe, if we ſticke not to commit grieuous and enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinnes; yea, if we endeuour not to liue vertuouſly, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vprightly, wee cannot hope to be ſaued: for as ſaith Saint Auguſtine moſt excellently, <hi>Firmiſſime tene &amp; nullate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dubites non omnes qui intra Eccleſiam Catholicam baptizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, accepturos eſſe vitam aeternam: ſed eos qui percepto baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate recte viuunt, id eſt, qui abſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uerunt ſe à vitijs &amp; concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentijs carnis. Regnum enim coelorum ſicut Infideles, Haeretic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> atque Schiſmatici non habebunt: ſic Catholici criminoſi poſſidere non poterunt.</hi> Hould it moſt firely, and doubt not any waies, that not all which are baptiſed within the Catholike Church ſhall receiue life euerlaſting: but they which being baptiſed liue well, that is, which haue abſtained from vices and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the fleſh. For the Kingdome of heauen, as faithleſſe Heretikes and Schiſmatikes ſhall not haue; ſo ſinfull Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes cannot poſſeſſe. God almighty vouchſafe to grant, that we which be Catholikes, may ſo order and diſpoſe our liues, as may be to the glory of God, edification of others, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our owne ſoules.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>PRAYERS FOR CONVERSION OF HE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RETIKES AND SCHISMATIKES.</head>
                     <p>
                        <q>OMnipotens aeterne Deus, erue quaeſimus Haereticos at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Schiſmaticos ab erronibus vniuerſis, &amp; ad ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam Matrem Eccleſiam Catholicam at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Apoſtolicam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocare digneris. Per Dominum noſtrum Ieſum Chriſtum Filium tuum qui tecum viuit &amp; regnat in ſaecula ſaeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Amen.</q>
                     </p>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Alia oratio.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q>OMnipotens aeterne Deus, qui ſaluas omnes, &amp; nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vis periro, reſpice ad animas, diabolica fraude
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177554:20"/> deceptas, vt omni haeretica prauitate depoſita, errantium corda recipiſcant, &amp; ad veritatis tuae redeant vnitatem. Per Dominum noſtrum Ieſum Chriſtum, &amp;c.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Alia oratio.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q>DEus qui errata corrigis, &amp; diſperſa congregas, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregata conſeruas, quaeſumus ſuper populum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianum tuae vnionis gratiam clementer infunde: vt diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione rejecta vero Paſtori Eccleſiae tuae ſe vniens, tibi dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne valeat famulari. Per Dominum noſtrum, &amp;c.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>OF THE TEMPORALL PROSPERITIE AND FELICITIE OF THEM WHICH haue defended the Church.</head>
                     <p>WE haue ſeene to what miſerable deſtruction diuers noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious enemies of God and his Church haue fallen: I could haue added hereunto moſt memorable examples of meaner, but yet honorable and worſhipfull Families, as alſo of diuers. Countries, Kingdomes and Peoples, which either in reſpect of their reuolt from the Catholike Church, or their oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the ſame, haue come to vtter ruine and deſolation. And is not this that the Prophet Iſay, or rather God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by the Prophet threatneth, Iſai. 60. 12. <hi>Gens, &amp; Regnum quod non ſeruierit tibi peribit,</hi> The Nation &amp; Kingdom which will not ſerue thee ſhall periſh: that is, ſuch Kingdomes and People as will not ſubject themſelues to the yoke of Chriſt, and obedience of his Church, ſhall periſh. Were not the moſt flouriſhing parts of the world for their fall to Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Donatiſme, Neſtorianiſme, and other condemned hereſies, for a juſt puniſhment of God ouer-runne and brought to deſolation by the Sarazens, and by infinite bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and ſauage people, Gothes, Vandals, Hunnes, Alanes, and others?</p>
                     <p>All Hiſtories are full of theſe matters, expreſſely ſetting downe the cauſe of the ouerthrow of ſo many goodly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177554:21"/> in Aſia, but eſpecially Africa; and in Europe, as Italy, Spaine, France, Germany, England, with other more.</p>
                     <p>Were not theſe goodly parts of the world, neere about vs, together with al Africa, ouerrun and deſtroyed by the Goths, Vandals, and other barbarous people, for Schiſme and Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie? Were not the Britons in this Iland, after they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with the Hereſie of Pelagius, thruſt out of their ſeates, moſt of them deſtroyed, and the remnant driuen into the barrenneſt parts of the Iland by the Saxons? And I ſhould neuer make an end, if I ſhould proceed to bring ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in this point, as are recorded in all ſorts of Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and writings extant in the world.</p>
                     <p>But now let vs relate ſome few examples of ſo many of the temporall proſperitie, and happy ſucceſſe of ſuch Princes as adhered to the Church, honored and defended it.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, thoſe noble victories are well knowne which are recorded in the old Teſtament, as the victories of Abraham, Moſes, Ioſua, Gedeon, Samuel, Dauid, Ezechias, Ioſias, and the Machabees.</p>
                     <p>In the new Teſtament, that is, in the Law of Grace, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the Great, which firſt of all the Emperours publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended the Church, almoſt in like ſort vanquiſhed Maxentius, as Moſes did Pharao; for Maxentius was drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Tyber, as Pharao in the Red-ſea. Euſeb. lib. 9. hiſt. cap. 9. Of him ſpeaketh Saint Auguſtine, <hi>lib. 5. de Ciuitate Dei, cap.</hi> 25. Conſtantine the Emperour not ſuppliant to Diuels, but worſhipping the true God, receiued ſo many gifts and bleſſings from God, as none durſt preſume to wiſh: this one Auguſtus held, poſſeſſed and defended the whole Romane Empire: In adminiſtring and making warre, hee was moſt victorious; in vanquiſhing and repreſſing Tyrants, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proſperous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being of great yeares, hee died of ſickneſſe and old age, and left ſonnes three, Emperours, to ſucceed him.</p>
                     <p>Of THEODOSIVS the elder, in the ſame place writeth the ſame S. Auguſt. cap. 26. that he had wonderfull ſucceſſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177554:21"/> in all his affaires, becauſe he was very pious and Catholike: that in the battels he fought with his enemies, their owne weapons, darts and arrowes, were retorted vpon the authors, God almighty fighting for him. Moreouer, L. Theodoret, in his fift booke of hiſtory, cap. 24. reporteth that S. Iohn and S. Philip the Apoſtles, appeared fighting for the Emperour Theodoſius in the ſame battell, riding vpon white horſes.</p>
                     <p>Of HONORIVS alſo, who was a moſt Catholike Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and moſt addicted to the Pope, as in his epiſtles to Pope Boniface appeareth, as writeth S. Aug. l. 5. de ciuit. Dei, c. 23. that God did ſo fight for him, as in one battell he ſlew of the Gothes aboue an hundred thouſand, and did take Radagai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the King, with his ſons, and put him to death: and (which was moſt admirable) there was not ſo much as one of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie either killed or wounded.</p>
                     <p>Of THEODOSIVS the yonger, writeth Socrat. l. 7. hiſt. cap. 18. that his armie skirmiſhing with the Barbarians, and himſelfe in the meane ſpace making his prayers vnto God within the city, about an hundred thouſand of the Sarazens were beaten and driuen by Angels into the riuer Euphrates, and ſo periſhed miſerably.</p>
                     <p>IVSTINTAN the elder, whileſt he was Catholike raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt proſperouſly, in ſo much as he reſtored to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire-Italy, Africk and many other Prouinces, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in Euagrius l. 4. hiſt. c. 26. &amp; ſequentibus. But after he became an Heretike, and purpoſed to ſet forth an Edict for receiuing of his hereſie, forthwith he died ſuddenly, and ſo deliuered the Church from great feare, as writeth the ſame Euagrius, lib. 4. cap. vlt.</p>
                     <p>HERACLIVS alſo, as appeareth in Zonoras, and other Hiſtoriographers, whileſt he was Catholike got a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and admirable victory againſt the Perſians, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the holy Croſſe, at which time the ſtate of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire was altogether deſperate; but after he fell into the hereſie of the Monothelites, he euer had euil ſucceſſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing euer ſucceeding with him, and himſelfe was extinct of a new and ſtrange diſeaſe.</p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:177554:22"/>
                     <p>Alſo it is manifeſt by the hiſtories of the Greekes, that the Emperours of the Eaſt, from that time, by reaſon of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion about Images, they diuided themſelues from the Church of Rome, ſtill decreaſed in power and authority, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till at laſt they vtterly loſt the Empire. And in the Weſt it is plaine by the hiſtories of the Latins, that the Emperours did more or leſſe flouriſh, as they were more or leſſe addicted to the Church of Rome.</p>
                     <p>In the time of VRBANE the ſecond, vnto the yeare of our Lord M. xcviij. the Chriſtians in that holy war made by the Pope for the recouery of Ieruſalem, when they were in moſt deſperate ſtate, becauſe of the approching of an infinite hoſte of the Turkes and Perſians, and they were but a few in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and wel-neare ſterued for lack of food; in ſo much as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the moſt valiant and ſtouteſt men did goe leaning vpon their ſtaues, neither had they but a few horſes, ſo as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of them, to wit, Godfrey was forced to borow a horſe, and many Princes were conſtrained to ride vpon Aſſes: at laſt God reuealed where was the Launce of Chriſt, and it being carried before them, gaue victory in the warre, in ſo much as there were ſlaine of the Turks an hundred thouſand, and ſcarſely foure thouſand of the Chriſtians loſt. And there fell from heauen a dewe vpon them, which comforted and refreſhed both their bodies and their ſoules. Finally, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared from heauen three holy men fighting for them. See Paulus Aemilius lib. 4. Guill. Tyr. lib. 6. neare the end, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dechimus, which continueth the ſtory of Marianus Scotus.</p>
                     <p>In the time of INNOCENTIVS the third, in France, of eight thouſand Catholikes, were ſlaine in one battell an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand of the Albigenſian Heretikes, as writeth Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius, lib 6. hiſt. Francor.</p>
                     <p>In our daies, 1531. the Catholikes of Heluetia fought fiue battels in defence of the Catholike faith, againſt the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes of Heluetia, and in euery one of them the Catholikes got the victory, whereas they were both in number and power farre inferiour to the Heretikes. See Io. Coclaeus in Act. Lutheri. 1531.</p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:177554:22"/>
                     <p>CHARLES the fift got a victory againſt the Lutherans, not without a miracle from heauen. Anno 1547.</p>
                     <p>Many other miraculous victories which the Catholikes haue got againſt Heretikes, both in France and other parts, might hereunto be annexed; but let theſe ſuffice.</p>
                     <q>Regi ſaeculorum immortali &amp; inuiſibili, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lt Deo honor &amp; gloria in ſaecula ſaeculorum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE ENDS OF BVRDEN OF DOVER, AND OTHERS HIS ASSOCIATS, WHICH IN THE beginning of Queene ELIZABETHS Raigne, went to Canterbury from Douer in deriſion and lewde <hi>ſort, to take their leaue of diuers Catholikes of Canterbury.</hi> Burden <hi>was the Controwler of the Cuſtome in Douer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1 BVRDEN being their Pope, within a few yeares after died at Douer in moſt lothſome and miſerable ſort, his friends which came to viſite him, were not able to abide the intollerable ſtincke of his body.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 STORER a Preacher, which caried the Pix, with ſome filthy thing in it; in their Proceſſion died at Maydſton in Kent, being the Preacher of that towne; he rotted from the toe vpwards vntill he died: he did ſauour ſo, as he was loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to all that in good will came to viſite him in his ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo moſt miſerably died at Maydſton.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 ROGER WOOD, the Towne-clerke of Douer being the Croſſe-bearer, died in Smith field at London, foming at the mouth, with his tongue hanging out in lothſome ſort, as bigge ſwolne as a bullocks tongue, and died moſt miſerably with his tongue hanging out of his mouth.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 MINGE<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Iurate of Douer, another of that lewde company, himſelfe ſitting at table eating, the loft ouer him fell downe, and preſſed him to death. His houſe was at the Peter at Douer, where this befell him.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 IOHN ROBBINS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Iurate of Douer, another of this company, being at Dunkyrk in Flanders, and putting his barke from the kaye of Dunkyrk, fell into the water, and bet<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
